<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Text Encoding Initiative public discussion list</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>January and February 1990 in the TEI Listserv
               <!-- TEI-L LOG9001, LOG9002 --></edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <!-- about the born-digital document -->
            <publisher>https://github.com/tei-cmc-experiment/tei-cmc-experiment</publisher>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
               <title level="s">TEI-L Listserv</title>
               <title level="s">LOG9001</title>
               <title level="s">LOG9002</title>
               <publisher>University of Illinois Chicago</publisher>
               <distributor>TEI-L@UICVM</distributor>
               <date>1990</date>
               <relatedItem type="archive">
                  <bibl>
                     <publisher>The Pennsylvania State University</publisher>
                     <distributor>LISTS.PSU.EDU LISTSERV Server (17.0)</distributor>
                     <date>2024</date>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Sampled by requesting monthly logs from <name type="API">LISTS.PSU.EDU</name> by
               e-mail with GET commands: <code>GET TEI-L LOG 9001</code> (for January 1990). One log
               command was issued for each month. See <ptr type="APIdoc"
                  target="https://www.lsoft.com/manuals/17.0/commands/14File-serverandwebfunctioncomma.html"
               />. Received by e-mail between <date from="2024-09-21" to="2024-09-22">September 21
                  and 22, 2024</date>.</p>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <TEI xml:id="Web-1990-01-31-0933">
      <teiHeader>
         <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
               <title type="subjectLine">compound documents and images</title>
               <author>Robert Philip Weber</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
               <p>Text Encoding Initative public discussion list</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
               <bibl><title level="a">LOG9001</title></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
         </fileDesc>
         <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
               <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <persName>Robert Philip Weber</persName>
                  <email>WEBER@HARVARDA.BITNET</email>
                  <date when="1990-01-31">Wed, 31 Jan 90 09:33:26 CST</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="relayed">
                  <orgName><ref target="mailto:TEI-L@UICVM">Text Encoding
                     Initative public discussion list</ref></orgName>
               </correspAction>            
            </correspDesc>
         </profileDesc>
      </teiHeader>
      <text>
         <body>
            <post>
               <p>could someone please explain the <name type="ML">TEI</name> approach to compound
                  documents and images? WIll <name type="ML">SGML</name> be used here, and if so,
                  how? I've just joined the list. sorry if this has been asked before.</p>
               <p>Many Thanks</p>
               <signed generatedBy="human">Bob Weber</signed>
               <signed generatedBy="template"> Robert Philip Weber, Ph.D. | Phone: (617) 495-3744
                  <lb/>Senior Consultant | Fax: (617) 495-0750 <lb/>Academic and Planning Services |
                  <lb/>Division | <lb/>Office For Information Technology| Internet:
                  weber@popvax.harvard.edu <lb/>Harvard University | Bitnet: Weber@Harvarda <lb/>50
                  Church Street | <lb/>Cambridge MA 02138 | </signed>               
            </post>
         </body>
      </text>
   </TEI>
   <TEI xml:id="Spe-1990-02-06-1054">
      <teiHeader>
         <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
               <title type="subjectLine">compound documents</title>
               <author>Michael Sperberg-McQueen</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
               <p>Text Encoding Initative public discussion list</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
               <bibl><title level="a">LOG9002</title></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
         </fileDesc>
         <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
               <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <persName>Michael Sperberg-McQueen</persName>
                  <email>U35395@UICVM.BITNET</email>
                  <date when="1990-02-06">Tue, 6 Feb 90 10:54:04 CST</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="relayed">
                  <orgName><ref target="mailto:TEI-L@UICVM">Text Encoding
                     Initative public discussion list</ref></orgName>
               </correspAction>  
               <correspContext>
                  <ref type="in-response-to" target="#Web-1990-01-31-0933">previous message of <persName>Robert Philip Weber</persName> to the TEI-L Listserv.
                  <date when="1990-01-31"/>
                  </ref>
               </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
         </profileDesc>
      </teiHeader>
      <text>
         <body>
            <post>
               <p>About compound documents in <name type="ML">SGML</name> and in the <name type="ML"
                  >TEI</name>. <ref target="#Web-1990-01-31-0933"><persName>R.P. Weber</persName>
                     asked a week ago <q>could someone please explain the <name type="ML">TEI</name>
                        approach to compound documents and images? WIll <name type="ML">SGML</name>
                        be used here, and if so, how?</q></ref></p>
               <p>Apologies for my delay in answering. I was hoping one of our hypertext sages might
                  weigh in with a reply. (But he appears to have been in the
                  <placeName>Caribbean</placeName>, and may not have received the query.)</p>
               <p>This problem has not, in fact, been discussed on this server, or as far as I'm
                  aware by the working committees. So the formal answer is that no decision has been
                  cast in concrete yet. Which allows me to turn the tables and say <q>How <emph
                     rend="*">should</emph> compound documents be encoded for interchange? What
                     are the requirements? What are the alternatives?</q></p>
               <p>Less formally, I can offer some personal opinions, for what they are worth (face
                  value: two cents -- 2u, for those of you on <objectName>IBM
                     mainframes</objectName> with real <objectName>IBM terminals</objectName>).</p>
               <p> Certainly <name type="ML">SGML</name> is where we should start in any search for
                  ways of handling compound objects, and I don't yet know any reason that SGML won't
                  provide a solution for the problem. I assume there are two methods of using <name
                     type="ML">SGML</name> in compound documents (correct me if I'm wrong): (1) use
                  <name type="ML">SGML</name> to organize the compound document (i.e. have an
                  SGML document which includes text, images, sound, etc. as its components), or (2)
                  use whatever-you-like to organize the compound document as a whole, and use <name
                     type="ML">SGML</name> as the notation for the textual components of the
                  compound document.</p>
               <p>For the simple case of text-with-illustrations, <name type="ML">SGML</name> seems
                  like a viable encoding mechanism (for the envelope and for the text components) to
                  me. It allows you to encode the graphics however you like, declaring your graphics
                  format as a non-<name type="ML">SGML</name> notation and declaring the contents of
                  your graphics elements (say 'PICTURE' or 'BLORT') as being data in that notation,
                  stored either within the <name type="ML">SGML</name> file or externally to it. You
                  get localization of the graphics within the text stream, integral or separate
                  storage of the graphics, and complete freedom to choose whatever graphic notation
                  you wish.</p>
               <p>As document encoding methods go, <name type="ML">SGML</name> is fairly hospitable
                  to graphics and other non-text pieces of compound objects. Nowhere in the standard
                  does it say that the data have to be words and characters. In fact, as far as I
                  know there is no <emph rend="*">explicit</emph> requirement in the standard that
                  an <name type="ML">SGML</name> document even has to be bytes in a computer. (Sure,
                  it's hard to understand the standard any other way, but that's not the same as an
                  explicit requirement.) <bibl>ISO 8879 par. 6.1 note 1</bibl> says in fact <q>This
                     International Standard does not constrain the physical organization of the
                     document within the data stream, message handling protocol, file system, etc.,
                     that contains it.</q> At the <eventName>SGML '89 conference</eventName> last
                  <date when="1989-10">October</date> in <placeName>Atlanta</placeName>, there
                  was a very nice paper by <persName>Douglas MacLeod</persName> (read by
                  <persName>Yuri Rubinsky</persName>) thinking about architectural designs as
                  <name type="ML">SGML</name> documents, which led to a general discussion of
                  <name type="ML">SGML</name> definitions for all sorts of objects, including
                  automobiles. Although most people (obviously) think of the <name type="ML"
                     >SGML</name> document as an electronic <emph rend="*">description</emph> of the
                  automobile (and the physical automobile as a side effect of processing), it
                  appears, in the light of the passage cited, hard to say categorically that an
                  automobile itself could never be parsed as an <name type="ML">SGML</name>
                  document. (If you could figure out how to define the delimiters.)</p>
               <p>The only hitch is that the <name type="ML">SGML</name> standard itself (<bibl
                  type="standard">ISO 8879</bibl>) does not specify in any detail what the
                  interface between <name type="ML">SGML</name> processors and non-<name type="ML"
                     >SGML</name> processors must, may, or can look like -- an advantage, if you
                  will, in that it doesn't constrain anyone to an inappropriate model, but a bit of
                  a disadvantage in that most people don't have a clue what they can now or will
                  eventually or might someday be able to do with SGML and graphics processors.</p>
               <p>Not being deeply involved in graphics work or compound documents myself, I don't
                  know off-hand what options are offered for this sort of thing by existing <name
                     type="ML">SGML</name> processors. There will certainly be a fierce market
                  demand for it, not only from humanists but also (to our great advantage) from the
                  defense industry, which needs <name type="ML">SGML</name> support for technical
                  manuals with diagrams (and of course cross-references and other hypertext
                  mechanisms) and has the small change to pay for the development costs. (As long as
                  they don't charge the humanists defense-contractor prices!)</p>
               <p>If for some reason one does <emph rend="*">not</emph> want to use <name type="ML"
                  >SGML</name> as the envelope for the entire compound document, then presumably
                  the major requirement for the text-components of the compound documents is that
                  they be computationally well-behaved, with a clearly defined structure, hooks for
                  pointers going out, and hooks for pointers coming in. SGML certainly has all of
                  this, in its document type declarations and its ID names and its IDREF
                  pointers.</p>
               <p>Perhaps those subscribers to this list who actually work with compound documents
                  and <name type="ML">SGML</name> will be willing to say how they make things work
                  now, and how they would like to see things developing in the future.</p>
               <p> All this is, I repeat, just personal opinion and shouldn't be taken as defining
                  <soCalled>the</soCalled> position of the <orgName>TEI</orgName>. (Unless, of
                  course, taking as <soCalled>the</soCalled> position will help get a discussion
                  started.)</p>
               <signed generatedBy="human">-Michael Sperberg-McQueen<lb/> University of Illinois at
                  Chicago </signed>
            </post>
         </body>
      </text>
      
   </TEI>
</TEI>